JOE: Let’s look in the process
of an Autism Assessment.
When an individual attends their
assessment, the assessor will
discuss any problems and the
interaction of the person will be
watched to look for potential signs.
There may need to be more appointments
to follow, and those who know the
individual well, will be asked for any
relevant information they can provide.
BETH: When the individual is a
child the school, nursery or GP
may be asked to fill in a report.
For a young person or adult, they may
be asked to fill in a questionnaire
about themselves with the GP supplying
any other medical information.
At the end of the process a report
will be produced, detailing whether
the individual meets the criteria
for Autism spectrum diagnosis, and
it will give information about what
help may be needed with communication,
social interaction and behaviours or
sensitivity and indicate any strengths.
JOE: If a formal assessment has been
done but it does not clearly show
whether or not they are on the spectrum,
or if someone disagrees with the
diagnosis, they can be referred again
or maybe have a private assessment.
Some individuals don’t want to go through
the process of a formal diagnosis and
may prefer to try an online autism test,
but these cannot guarantee accuracy.
BETH: Informal assessments of individuals
with autism spectrum disorders
involve the collection of information
about the individual, interpreting
that information so as to better
understand the individual’s abilities.
Informal assessment is usually about
gaining information in order to set goals,
identify strategies, and measure outcomes.
Although the overall goals of informal
and formal assessment are similar,
they differ in the manner, type and
use, of the information collected.
JOE: In the past formal assessment
was broken down into different
diagnoses such as Aspergers syndrome,
Autistic disorder, Kanner’s syndrome,
childhood autism, atypical autism
and pervasive developmental disorder
not otherwise specified [PDD-NOS].
These all now come under the term
Autism spectrum disorder [ASD] or
Autism for short, for all diagnoses.
BETH: The emphasis now on diagnosis is
the specific ‘levels' of Autism spectrum
disorder, allowing for more clarity to be
placed on where they fit on the spectrum.
The levels range from
mild to severe symptoms.
JOE: There are three levels of autism:
- Level 1 requiring some support;
- Level 2 requiring substantial support
- Level 3 requiring very substantial support
These levels are based on a person's
strengths and limitations in regard to
their ability to communicate, adapt to
new situations, expand beyond restricted
interests, and manage daily life.
BETH: Although the levels of support are
useful for indicating where an autistic
person falls on the spectrum regarding
severity, they have their limitations.
They can be very subjective, for example,
some may need support at school but are
fine at home, while others may do well at
school but struggle in social situations.
It is therefore up to the clinicians to
identify the individual support needed
for each person that is diagnosed.